all right so why should you listen to a
random guy in a white T-shirt standing
in front of a whiteboard my name's Matt
I'm a current strategy and operations
Associated Google prior to that was a
consultant at BCG and I make these
videos because I enjoy it but also
because I want to share with you what
I've learned so that you can hopefully
land your dream job today we're going to
talk about case interview math and
specifically what kind of math is needed
some best practices when it comes to the
case interview and finally some tips and
tricks for doing the actual math in the
interview let's get right into it all
right so the first question we need to
answer before we even think about math
is first of all what kind of math is
even needed right because I think
sometimes people get a little bit
intimidated by the math and the reality
is that the math is not super complex
basically all you need to know is basic
algebra and the ability to multiply and
divide large numbers as well as to deal
with percentages and so nothing you
learned in calculus or linear algebra or
any of those other advanced math classes
if you're a math major is going to
really apply to case interviews so often
when I explain this to people I get a
lot of comments about oh Consulting math
is so easy like anyone can do it and I
would say that yes that's true the math
itself is not inherently that difficult
and doesn't require you to have a PhD to
complete but what really matters is how
you interpret the numbers and how you
use them in the context of the case and
so for example two people can come to
the same exact number but one person can
explain it in a way that makes more
sense than the other person and
therefore do better in the interview and
so for example if we learned that
company a does 5 million in sales and we
know the total Market is 200
million dollar then an okay candidate
might arrive at this number and say okay
awesome so I've learned that company a
does 5 million in sales and I think that
that's a really big number and so I
would say that they're doing relatively
well however a smarter candidate would
take this number in the context of other
data points including this one and say
well okay this is interesting it looks
like company a does about 5 million in
sales per year and so that's pretty good
but I can also see that the entire
Market is 200 million So currently they
have less than 1% of the entire market
and so that could mean a couple of
things it could mean that they have a
lot of room to grow or it could mean
that there is some other reason why they
have such a small market share maybe
they've just entered the market for
example but if they've been around for a
while then maybe there's some sort of
structural issue with their business and
so that's an example of why even though
the math might not be the most advanced
you're never being truly tested on just
the accuracy of your calculations you're
also being tested on how you think about
that number in relation to other data
points given in the case and that makes
sense right because any number or data
point that you get is just one single
discrete data point and so it doesn't
have as much meaning unless you compare
it to a set of other data points like
for example if you tell me hey Matt I
have $10 million what should I do with
it well without additional information
and additional data points on who you
are and what stage of life you're at and
potentially what your goals are then how
can anyone give you a solid
recommendation for what you should do
with your money like obviously some
people be like yeah you should invest
other people will be like oh you should
spend it or some people like oh just
like put it under your pillow and none
of these by themselves are inherently
bad recommendations they all have pros
and cons but they might not be the best
recommendation for you because your
specific situation maybe you just happen
to be like an
18-year-old and you know you're not from
a wealthy background and you need the
financial stability and you have lowrisk
tolerance Etc so all this is to say we
basically need to take the number not in
isolation as discret points but we also
need to really consider them in the
context of other numbers in the case but
now that we know what kind of math is
needed in most case interviews the next
question you might be having is why do I
even need to be tested on this math it
seems very basic right and that's a
valid question and what I would say to
that is nowadays most people in business
roles whether be consulting or other
jobs in corporate never actually do math
by hand or mentally there always using
some sort of tools or some sort of
program whether it be Excel or a
calculator to do the math and so when
you're actually working full-time you're
rarely going to ever actually have to do
mental math or quick math by hand but
despite that the reason why consulting
firms still test you in case interview
math is because one it gives them a
sense of your quantitative aptitude can
you think quickly and make estimates
without needing to consult your
financial model for example like the
bottom line is you have to be somewhat
good at math you don't need to be a
genius but you need to be somewhat good
at at basic math in order to do this job
well but the second piece is how this
translates to on the job and so there
are a number of situations in Consulting
where you you might need to make a quick
calculation and a common example that
often comes up is in a client meeting
now oftentimes it's going to be your
managing director who is running this
meeting but say for example the client
shows them a set of data or shows them
the results of some survey that they've
just run and you guys have never seen it
before but it's interesting your
managing director might try to basically
interpret that data and do some quick
calculations to basically try and draw
out some key insights that maybe the
team will then go ahead and build out a
more complex analysis later additionally
when you're a junior consultant on the
job you almost always want to be sanity
checking your work after you do any sort
of analysis and this can just be a lot
easier sometimes if you don't have to
always whip out a calculator or use
Excel to check something and finally I
would just say that testing you on math
in an inter view is good at assessing
your speed and your accuracy with
numbers now speed and accuracy is the
name of the game when it comes to jobs
like consulting or Investment Banking
because you're often under a very short
timeline to get a lot of work done and
so you need to be obviously fast and
able to produce a lot of output but also
there's no point in producing a lot of
output if it's inaccurate and so the
math that is tested although I would say
it's not a perfect assessment of how
someone will perform on the job it is
one proxy of how fast can you be and how
accurate can you be in a high press
situation okay but now that we've
established what kind of math is needed
and why we are being tested on math the
next question is when we are doing the
math in case interviews how should we do
it and the answer here is whenever you
are in a case interview scenario you
always want to structure out the
basically logic of the equation that you
are then going to plug the inputs into
after before you do any sort of math now
the reason that you don't want to do the
math upfront is because first of all
best practices are that you should run
the logic by your interviewer first to
ensure that it makes sense to them and
also to ensure that you're not making
any mistakes because they can give you
feedback if you are and second is
because the thought process itself is
just as important if not more important
than the actual execution of calculating
those numbers themselves in case
interviews you're not necessarily being
tested on oh did he get to this exact
number it's more about the methodology
and the process by which you got to that
result and so I would argue that
demonstrating very clear thinking is
just as important if not more than
demonstrating that you can actually do
the calculations and so I've basically
laid these three steps out here but
again we got to build the logic out
first and then we have to walk through
it with the interviewer before we
actually do the math and the big thing
here is we need to demonstrate clear
thinking and also good communic
communication many people underestimate
this aspect of the case interview by
good communication I'm talking about do
you speak aloud and explain every step
of your thought process in a logical
ordered way to your interviewer such
that they can understand what you're
talking about and they're not confused
and having to ask clarifying questions
do they understand exactly what you are
going to do and how you are going to do
it and do they understand why you're
doing it that way and are you able to
communicate that confidently and in a
way that demonstrates them that if you
were to be dropped off in a client
meeting you wouldn't make a fool of
yourself and you would be able to walk
the CEO or whoever the client is through
the work that you've been doing and the
analysis that you've been building that
is what is also being tested at the same
time that you are doing the quantitative
portion of a case the math itself is not
supposed to be the difficult part what
you are being tested on is not just if
you can get to the right number it is
also how you communicate it and how you
structure your problem solving approach
to demonstrate to the interviewer that
you can come up with a repeatable
methodology for solving these problems
but now with all that in mind let's talk
about some actual tips and tricks that
can be helpful when it comes to actually
doing the math in a case interview
scenario where you're not going to have
a lot of time you're not going to have
access to a calculator and you're going
to have the interview basically staring
at you and so you might be feeling more
pressure than you would if you were just
doing this math alone in a room now the
first one is don't use zeros now this
might come as not a surprise for some of
you but I'm just going to say it because
I'm assuming zero knowledge of case
interviews here and what I will say is
you'll often get really really large
numbers in the millions or the billions
of dollars or units and so quick rule of
thumb is you always want to use
abbreviations if you can use billions
use Millions use you know k for
thousands never ever ever write out the
zeros because you are literally just
going to waste time and also there's a
lot of issues and errors that you can
make if you have a ton of zeros on your
paper just remember that billion is nine
zeros million is 6 zeros K is three and
when you calculate large numbers where
maybe you're multiplying or dividing
Millions by billions it's super
important to keep track of how many
zeros you need in your final result and
so for example if we were going to do
something like 40 million times 6,000
what we can do here is we can multiply
the four and the six which you know is
24 and then we know there's 10 zeros
after it so I'm just going to do * 10 to
the 10th okay and 10 the 10th which is
also 240 ion now another person might
have written out all the 10 zeros after
this but again that would be pretty
timec consuming and if you just remember
that a billion has nine zeros then you
would know that okay 24 * 10 10th that's
basically the same as 240 * 10 9th which
is a billion and so that's how I know
it's 240 billion but just a simple
example for you now the second tip I
have is round numbers where possible now
I think a lot of people already sort of
know that you should be rounding numbers
where possible but I think another thing
that can really help you take it to the
next level is is when you are rounding
numbers and you're telling your
interviewer hey for example I want to
take 32.5 and actually round it down to
30 what a okay candidate would say is oh
so I'm actually going to round down to
30 because that's a little bit easier to
manage now there's nothing wrong with
that explanation but if you want to take
it a step further what you should really
do here is you should give some sort of
reason why it makes sense to round down
to 32 rather than just oh it's easier
for the math so a basic example of this
would be hey maybe this 32.5 represents
the number of people in a day that on
average are entering a store but you
know that the store that you're
currently evaluating is actually in a
location where it's a little bit off of
the the Main Street and there's slightly
lower foot traffic and so what you could
say to your interviewer is hey so I know
we've been given that 32.5 is the
average number of people that typically
enter this type of a store but given the
additional information that we know
about the store location it's a little
bit further from the main shopping
street I would imagine we should be a
little bit more conservative and assume
that there's less foot traffic going
into this store on average and so I
think it makes sense to round down to 30
instead of using 32 and A2 that is an
example of taking it one step further
than just saying oh I'm going to round
just because it's easier for the math
instead you give a legit reason based on
the context of the case for why it makes
sense for you to round up or to round
down now the third tip that I have for
math is you should always break numbers
apart now what do I mean by that well
often times you're going to be asked to
to do things like double- digit
multiplication or just multiplying
numbers that aren't perfectly round and
so I want to show you a quick trick that
can help you really simplify the math
and so for example if we have something
like 55 * 60 we can break this out into
basically 50 * 60 plus 5 * 60 and so we
know that 50 * 60 is 3,000 and we know
that 5 * 60 is 300 and so the answer is
3,300 and so you should always be
looking for opportunities to break
numbers apart in order to simplify the
calculations for yourself and to avoid
making unnecessary errors now another
pretty helpful tip for multiplying
numbers is cross multiplication and I'm
going to start squatting here so for
example if you have something like 31 *
12 one way that you could do this is you
could do it the traditional way of
multiplying it like this and having
multiple steps but there is a trick to
make this a little bit quicker and so
the trick is that you first multiply the
digits in the ones place to get the last
digit then you multiply the digits in
the 10 place to get the first digit and
finally for the middle you have to cross
multiply so we're going to multiply
these two digits and we're going to add
them together and so 1 + 6 is 7 so for
example 31 * 12 I know is 372 now
because I did the cross multiplication
trick and so this is another pretty
quick way to multiply double- digit
numbers together that can be helpful
sometimes in a case interview but one
other thing that I haven't discussed is
how to deal with percentages and so
often times in a case interview scenario
in addition to obviously having to
multiply and divide large numbers with
many digits you're also going to have to
do some sort of calculations with
percentages and so again when you
encounter percentages the first thing
you want to think about is is there an
opportunity for me to break the
percentages apart such that it makes the
calculation a little bit easier for me
let me give you an example let's say for
example that we need to calculate 15% of
60 million now one way is you could do
it the the normal way and try to
multiply .1 5 * 60 million but how we
can make this easier for ourselves is we
can break 15% into 10% and 5% and so
this is actually 10% and 5% right and so
if we can take 10% of 60 million and 5%
of 60 million and then add those
together then that'll get us to the same
result and it's much easier to get 10%
of any number again because we just have
to remove a zero and so we know that 10%
of 60 is just six and 5% is just half of
10% so we know that's three so then we
know that this is actually nine and
don't forget that the millions and so we
were very easily able to get to 15% of
60 million by just breaking the 15% into
just 10% and 5% and just adding those
two together now another way that this
can work is if say for example you need
to do
35% of 80 million right now in this case
it's not as simple as breaking into just
10% and 5% but what we can remember is
that 35% that's basically 5% times seven
right and so if we can just get 5% of 80
million and then multiply that number by
seven then we can also get to the result
and 5% is half of 10% and so 10% of 80
is 8 divide by two that's four and so we
know this is four * 7 gets us 28 and
don't forget again to add the million so
we know that 35% of 80 million is 28
million so again always be looking for
opportunities to break apart the
percentages because it's going to make
your life so much easier when it comes
to calculating x% of some giant number
all right so now that I've showed you
some tricks you might still be wondering
what do I do if I get stuck or if I get
the wrong answer in a case interview now
the first thing is just stay calm take a
deep breath and again ask your
interviewer for feedback and if they say
for example oh maybe you should check
your math again or oh I think there
might be a better way to do this then
this is your cue that you should go back
and check your math and so the way I
would do this is I would say all right
so it looks like I've gotten to this say
65 Million number but let me take a
moment now to double check my work and
so what I would do is I would then walk
the interviewer through the entire logic
of your equation again and again if they
agree and still say yeah that sounds
good to me then the issue is probably
not with how you structured the math but
it's with how you actually did the
calculations and so that's a good thing
because then you can just go back and
again check your math and go through
slowly talk aloud and again tell them
what you're doing walk them through the
process say hey I'm taking 15% of 65
million and that gets me to X and
ideally this should allow you to
identify the problem where you went
wrong now some common issues that I see
with math are people again they use too
many zeros or they get messed up with
the zeros and they they leave one out or
they add an additional zero in which
then increases or decreases your result
by an order of magnitude but sometimes
people also make basic multiplication or
division mistakes as well and so
honestly don't stress you're often much
more nervous in a case interview than
you are when you are preparing and say
in your room or in the library and so
it's okay if you make some mistakes now
that said if you are currently in the
thick of the case in grind and you think
you might benefit from a little bit of
help I do offer one-on-one coaching
where I can give you tailored
personalized feedback and guide you
through the process one-on-one if that
sounds interesting to you then just feel
free to check out the link in the
description but otherwise thanks for
dropping by I'll see you guys in the
next one peace